Guide to the John Gunther Papers 1935-1967
University of Chicago Library
- Series XIV: Inside Europe Today
  - Subseries 7: Miscellaneous Manuscripts
    - "Prime Minister of England," written and published sometime in 1959, basis of chapter 16 on Harold Macmillan in published book. (Box 112, Folder 11)
    - "Meet Your Neighbor-Greece"-excerpt from Chapter 12 of published book (Box 112, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript pages and fragments (Box 112, Folder 13)
    - Advertising description of Inside Europe Today (Box 112, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 8: Correspondence
    - Informational correspondence-A-Z (Box 112, Folder 15)
    - Suggested revisions of manuscript and galley by editors and "specialists" (Box 112, Folder 16)
    - Recording disk of memorandum to Book-of-the-Month Club (Box 112, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 9: Research Notes-Germany
    - Interview notes, "Barr" Charles Blackman (U.S. official) Willy Brandt (Mayor, West Berlin) Gaston Coblentz (Correspondent) (Box 113, Folder 1)
    - Interview notes, "R.D." [Robert Doty?] Ludwig Erhardt (Minister of Economics) M. W. Fodor (Correspondent) Meyer Friedrich (Box 113, Folder 2)
    - Interview notes, Hans Globke (Secretary of State, Chancellor's Office "Gorday" Dr. Hines (Amerika Haus) "Kaplan" "Kecklin" (Box 113, Folder 3)
    - Interview notes, "Pope" [Sam Pope Brewer?] "Rosie" Carlo Schmid (Social Democrat leader) "Schweinitz" (Box 113, Folder 4)
    - Interview notes, "Stearman" Christopher Steele (British Ambassador) Stefan Themas (Box 113, Folder 5)
    - Interview notes, Miscellaneous (Box 113, Folder 6)
    - Notes on Berlin briefing (Box 113, Folder 7)
    - Notes on trip to East Berlin (Box 113, Folder 8)
    - Notes on Adenauer, RIAS, West Berlin, Bonn (Box 113, Folder 9)
    - Outlines (Box 113, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 113, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 10: Research Notes-France
    - Interview notes, Georges Bonnet (politician) "Desnoyer" (Box 113, Folder 12)
    - Interview notes, "R.D." [Robert Doty?] (Box 113, Folder 13)
    - Interview notes, M. W. Fodor (Correspondent) (Box 113, Folder 14)
    - Interview notes, Walter Kerr (Correspondent) "Korry" Jean Monnet (Common Market leader) (Box 113, Folder 15)
    - Interview notes, David Schoenbrun (radio commentator) "Guy S." Ed Taylor (correspondent) (Box 113, Folder 16)
    - Interview notes, Miscellaneous (Box 113, Folder 17)
    - Notes on De Gaulle, Algeria and French Africa (Box 113, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous notes, Outline (Box 113, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 11: Research Notes-Italy
    - Interview notes, "British Lunch" "Cippico" Ashley Clark "Fuacco" (Box 113, Folder 20)
    - Interview notes, Giovanni Gronchi (President of Republic) "Homes" "McGurn" (correspondent) (Box 113, Folder 21)
    - Interview notes, Giovanni Malogodi (Secretary, Liberal Party) "Martinelli" Robert Neville (journalist) Miscellaneous (Box 113, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous notes, outlines (Box 113, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 12: Research Notes-England
    - Interview notes, "N. Bicknell" R. A. Butler (Home Secretary) William Clark (Box 114, Folder 1)
    - Interview notes, Richard Crossman (Labour party) "Demarest" "Evans" (S. H. Evans. Macmillan aide?) Michael Foote (Labour Party) (Box 114, Folder 2)
    - Interview notes, Hugh Gaitskell (Leader, Labour Party) Q. M. Hogg, Lord Hailsham (Minister for Science) Denis Healy (Labour Party) "Hooke" (Box 114, Folder 3)
    - Interview notes, "Jock" Selwyn Lloyd (Foreign Minister) Iain Macleod (Colonial Secretary) Harold Macmillan (Prime Minister) Drew Middleton (correspondent) C. B. Ormerod (British Information Service) (Box 114, Folder 4)
    - Interview notes, "Sanders" "Gary S." William Whitney Paul Wright "Z" (Phil de Zuelita?) Miscellaneous (Box 114, Folder 5)
    - Notes on Macmillan, Conservative Party, Tory leaders (Box 114, Folder 6)
    - Notes on Labour Party, Labour leaders, Defense, Miscellaneous, Outlines (Box 114, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 13: Research Notes-Russia
    - Interview notes, Chester Bohlen (U.S. Ambassador) M. W. Fodor (journalist) Jean Monnet (Common Market leader) Edward R. Murrow (commentator) Harrison Salisbury (journalist) Henry Schapiro (journalist) Miscellaneous (Box 114, Folder 8)
    - Notes on the Summit Conference-Khrushchev at Summit, U-2 affair; at United Nations; Khrushchev (Box 114, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous notes; outlines (Box 114, Folder 10)
    - Satellites-Notes on Hungary; Albania-Bulgaria, Rumania, Czechoslovakia; Poland; Yugoslavia (Box 114, Folder 11)
    - Austria-Interview notes; miscellaneous notes (Box 114, Folder 12)
    - Belgium-Notes on the Congo; miscellaneous notes (Box 114, Folder 13)
    - Greece-Miscellaneous notes; notes on Cyprus (Box 114, Folder 14)
    - Iberian Peninsula-Spain; Portugal-Miscellaneous notes (Box 114, Folder 15)
    - Luxembourg; Netherlands-Miscellaneous notes (Box 114, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 14: Research Notes-Scandinavia
    - Denmark-miscellaneous notes, Finland-miscellaneous notes Iceland-miscellaneous notes Norway-miscellaneous notes Sweden-miscellaneous notes Switzerland-miscellaneous notes (Box 115, Folder 1)
    - Turkey-miscellaneous notes (Box 115, Folder 2)
    - Common Market-Jean Monnet (founder), Common Market-Miscellaneous (Box 115, Folder 3)
    - Common Market-Miscellaneous notes (Box 115, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 15: Research Notes-NATO
    - Interview notes, Hanson Baldwin (journalist) (Box 115, Folder 5)
    - Interview notes, Hugh Gaitskell (Labour Party leader) Edward Murrow (commentator) "Stearman" "Cy" (C. L. Sulzberger-journalist?) - Miscellaneous (Box 115, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes, outlines (Box 115, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous general notes, adds, watch sheets (Box 115, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous general notes, watch sheets, check sheets, proof sheets (Box 115, Folder 9)
    - Outlines, agenda, idea sheets (Box 115, Folder 10)
    - Typewritten notes by author (Box 115, Folder 11)
    - Typewritten notes by others (Box 115, Folder 12)
- Series XV: Juvenile Books
  Included with the Juvenile Books, is the manuscript for DAYS TO REMEMBER-AMERICA 1945-1955, a pictorial book published in 1956, written by Gunther in collaboration with Bernard Quint, the associate art editor of Life. Only the manuscripts for this work are part of the collection. Much of the text was in the form of captions for the 400 or more photographs in the volume. The manuscripts are as follows:
  1. Original manuscript, in longhand by author, with corrections
  2. First Revision or Second Draft, typed and heavily revised by author.
  Gunther wrote three children's books on historical and mythical characters. They are ALEXANDER THE GREAT. published in 1953, JULIUS CAESAR, and THE GOLDEN FLEECE, the latter two published in 1959, Obviously, there are no interview notes for these works. Only the original manuscript of ALEXANDER THE GREAT, which is very heavily revised, is a part of the collection. Two manuscripts of JULIUS CAESAR are included in the collection:
  1. Original manuscript, typed by the author and very heavily revised
  2. First Revision or Second Draft, which is also very heavily revised.
  The manuscripts of THE GOLDEN FLEECE are of special interest. In the original manuscript, Gunther faithfully recounted the gory legend of Jason and Medea, but subsequently toned down the bloodthirstiness in later drafts. The manuscripts are as follows:
  1: Original manuscript, in longhand by the author with corrections:
  2. First Revision or Second Draft, typed and heavily revised
  3. Second Revision or Third Draft, which is also heavily revised by author.
  Gunther has also written a series of juvenile works on Africa, which are revised versions for younger readers of some of his chapters from INSIDE AFRICA. He has written a revised version of INSIDE RUSSIA TODAY, entitled MEET SOVIET RUSSIA, published in two volumes in 1962. However, only the manuscripts for MEET THE CONGO are included in the collection. The manuscripts are as follows:
  1. First Revision or Second Draft, with corrections by author
  2. Printer's copy, with author's corrections.
  - Subseries 1: Days to Remember
    - Original manuscript (Box 116, Folder 1)
    - Original manuscript (Box 116, Folder 2)
    - Original manuscript (Box 116, Folder 3)
    - 2nd draft (Box 116, Folder 4)
    - 2nd draft (Box 116, Folder 5)
    - 2nd draft (Box 116, Folder 6)
    - Retyped pages (Box 116, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Alexander the Great
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 1-5 (Box 116, Folder 8)
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 6-12 (Box 116, Folder 9)
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 13-20 (Box 116, Folder 10)
    - Outlines, corrections of manuscript and comments (Box 116, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3: The Golden Fleece
    - Original Manuscript (Box 116, Folder 12)
    - 2nd Draft (Box 116, Folder 13)
    - 3rd Draft (Box 116, Folder 14)
    - Corrections of manuscript and comments (Box 116, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 4: Meet the Congo
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 1-4 (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 5-7 (Box 117, Folder 2)
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 8-11 (Box 117, Folder 3)
    - Printer's Copy-Chapters 1-3 (Box 117, Folder 4)
    - Printer's Copy-Chapters 4-7 (Box 117, Folder 5)
    - Printer's Copy-Chapters 8-9 (Box 117, Folder 6)
    - Printer's Copy-Chapters 10-12 (Box 117, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 5: Julius Caesar
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 1-9 (Box 117, Folder 8)
    - Original Manuscript-Chapters 10-17 (Box 117, Folder 9)
    - 2nd Draft-Chapters 1-9 (Box 117, Folder 10)
    - 2nd Draft-Chapters 10-19 (Box 117, Folder 11)
    - Retyped pages (Box 117, Folder 12)
    - Corrections of manuscript and comments (Box 117, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence on juvenile books (Box 117, Folder 14)
- Series XVI: Correspondence
  Included among the Papers of John Gunther are two boxes of correspondence, mostly between Gunther and his publishers, Harper and Brothers and Hamish Hamilton. Gunther said of this correspondence-"My friends at Harper's perhaps exaggerate, but they say that they have no knowledge of any other file which shows so intimately and over such a sustained period the various factors which are constantly at play in the relationship between a publisher and an author-literary, financial, editorial, etc." The correspondence covers the years from 1936 to 1961. However, the material from 1936 to 1949 is more complete, coming from the files of Harper and Brothers. The post-1949 correspondence was extracted from the original deposit and had been scattered throughout the collection with each specific book, but was brought together in this section. The correspondence deals mostly with publishing matters, but several of the letters contain some of Gunther's views on history, economic theory and other matters. The material has been arranged chronologically.
  There is also some miscellaneous correspondence concerned with requests for autographs, asking Gunther to speak at meetings or to contribute articles to journals, or simply friendly letters telling Gunther how much the reader has enjoyed all of his books. Some of the Letters refer to articles Gunther has written in popular magazines or are responses to his television show "High Road."
  - Subseries 1: Harper & Bros. (Hamish Hamilton)
    - 1935 (Box 118, Folder 1)
    - January-March 1936 (Box 118, Folder 2)
    - April-December 1936 (Box 118, Folder 3)
    - March-December 1937 (Box 118, Folder 4)
    - 1938 (Box 118, Folder 5)
    - 1939 (Box 118, Folder 6)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 118, Folder 7)
    - 1942 (Box 118, Folder 8)
    - 1943 (Box 118, Folder 9)
    - 1944 (Box 118, Folder 10)
    - 1945 (Box 118, Folder 11)
    - January-June 1946 (Box 118, Folder 12)
    - July-October 1946 (Box 118, Folder 13)
    - November-December 1946 (Box 118, Folder 14)
    - January-February 1947 (Box 118, Folder 15)
    - March-April 1947 (Box 118, Folder 16)
    - May 1-May 15, 1947 (Box 118, Folder 17)
    - May 16-May 31, 1947 (Box 118, Folder 18)
    - June 1947 (Box 118, Folder 19)
    - July-September 1947 (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - October-December 1947 (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - January-June 1948 (Box 119, Folder 3)
    - July-December 1948 (Box 119, Folder 4)
    - January-March 1949 (Box 119, Folder 5)
    - April-December 1949 (Box 119, Folder 6)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 119, Folder 7)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 119, Folder 8)
    - 1955-1957 (Box 119, Folder 9)
    - 1953-1961 (Box 119, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - A-B (Box 119, Folder 11)
    - C-F (Box 119, Folder 12)
    - G (Box 119, Folder 13)
    - H (Box 119, Folder 14)
    - I-L (Box 119, Folder 15)
    - M (Box 119, Folder 16)
    - N-P (Box 119, Folder 17)
    - R-S (Box 119, Folder 18)
    - T-Z (Box 119, Folder 19)
- Series XVII: Chicago Revisited
  Chicago Revisited was commissioned and masterminded by Fairfax M. Cone, chairman of the University of Chicago Board of Trustees, and Carl Larsen, director for Public Relations. John Gunther, an alumnus, was asked to write an essay capturing his impressions of the University. The work would be based upon Gunther's visit to the Midway in April 1964 and information compiled by Larsen's office, including faculty profiles.
  Gunther's first draft, submitted to Larsen in June 1964, was ready by Cone, who made suggestions as to changes. Many of these were incorporated into a "first revision", authored by Larsen's office. This version was then circulated among administrators and faculty, who were solicited for comments. The "second revision", based on these remarks, was subsequently sent to Gunther for reworking. His final manuscript was published by the University in May 1967. Condensed versions of Chicago Revisited also appeared as articles in Chicago Today, Saturday Review, and Midwest magazines
  - Original manuscript (Box 120, Folder 1)
  - Revision of original manuscript suggested by Fairfax M. Cone (Box 120, Folder 2)
  - Rough draft of first revision (Box 120, Folder 3)
  - Fair copy of first revision (Box 120, Folder 4)
  - Comment by various administrators and faculty members (Box 120, Folder 5)
  - First revision with comments, labeled "notes-2nd revision" (Box 120, Folder 6)
  - First revision marked with agreed changes, labeled "rough draft-2nd version" (Box 120, Folder 7)
  - Fair copy of second revision (Box 120, Folder 8)
  - JG's rewrite of second revision (Box 120, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript of final version (October 13, 1964) (Box 120, Folder 10)
  - Condensed version of Gunther article used by Chicago Today and Saturday Review (Box 121, Folder 1)
  - Suggested showcase paragraphs for condensed article in Midwest magazine (Box 121, Folder 2)
  - Faculty profiles-Bettelheim-Friedman (Box 121, Folder 3)
  - Faculty profiles-Hauser-Morgenthau (Box 121, Folder 4)
  - Faculty profiles-Mulliken-Simpson (Box 121, Folder 5)
  - Faculty profiles-Stigler-Zachariasen (Box 121, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, December 1963-May 1964 (Box 121, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, June-August, 1964 (Box 121, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, September 1964-June 1965 (Box 121, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, July 1965-July 1966 (Box 121, Folder 10)
  - Proposed covers for manuscript (Box 121, Folder 11)
  - Reprints of Gunther articles in two Japanese magazines (Box 121, Folder 12)
  - "Inside the Midway," in Midwest (December 12, 1965) (Box 121, Folder 13)
  - "Chicago Revisited," in Chicago Today (Spring, 1965) (Box 121, Folder 14)
  - "An Old Grad Returns to Chicago" in Saturday Review (October 16, 1965) (Box 121, Folder 15)
  - JG manuscript, "The Fun of Writing the Inside Books" (Box 122, Folder 1)
  - JG memos on his books, submitted to the University of Chicago (Box 122, Folder 2)
  - Behind the Curtain, 1949 edition (Box 122, Folder 3)
  - Inside U.S.A., 1947 edition, autographed (Box 122, Folder 4)